Cancer "cures" collection
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
Cancer "cures" collection
1900-1954
Pam Coll 10
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
1
Collection consists of pamphlets and books by individuals, private cancer hospitals, and other organizations promoting non-surgical cures for cancer. The American Medical Association claimed that any such cures were fakes. The promoters in turn criticized the AMA as the "medical trust." Most of the pamphlets contain patient testimonials. Approximate dates for items are based on the date of the most recent testimonials.
Arrangement
Single series arranged by last name of individual or corporate name.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by William Helfand, 2013-2014.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are available for research. Yale does not own copyright.
Related Materials
There are additional advertisements for cancer cures in the William Helfand Collection of Medical Ephemera (Pam Coll 8), Album 2. See also Harry M. Hoxsey, How Dr. Hoxsey wins and loses (Wichita, Kansas, 1956). Hoxsey was a notorious promotor of a cancer cure. The pamphlet is about court cases against him.
Cancer; Cancer -- Hospitals; Cancer -- Treatment; Krebiozen; Quacks and quackery; Advertisements -- Medicine; Pamphlets; Cancer cure fakes; Facts about cancer; Liquid escharotic with combinations for the proper treatment of cancers, tumors, ulcers, lupus and abnormal growths without chloroform or ether; Successful cure for cancer; Cancer profiteers: suppression of truth; TNT Magazine; Value of escharotics; Baker, Norman, 1882-1958; Helfand, William H.; Leach, Leon T.; Mason, Abbott Myron; McNeill, Charles A.; Nichols, Perry, 1863-1925; Root, Charles C.; Seaman, R. C., 1878-; Smith, G. F. (George Franklin); Southworth, H. C.; Tomlinson, William Hoare; Williams, Boyd T.; American Medical Association; Baker Hospital (Eureka Springs, Ark,); Cherokee Sanitarium (Cherokee, Iowa); Dr. Nichols Sanatorium (Savannah, Mo.); Indianapolis Cancer Hospital; Industrial Clinic (New York, N.Y.); Krebiozen Research Foundation (Chicago, Ill,); Mason Cancer Institute (New York, N.Y.); Abbott Myron Mason Chemical Co; Park View Sanatorium (Indianapolis, Ind.); Williams Sanatorium, Inc. (Minneapolis, Minn.)
- American Medical Association, Cancer Cure Fakes, ca. 1909 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  The subtitle is "Eight Concerns Against Which the United States Post-Office Has Issued Fraud Orders." Chapters on various supposed non-surgical cures. The AMA claimed any "cure" by medication alone was quackery.
- Norman Baker, Muscatine, Iowa, 1927-1930 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Two issues of TNT Magazine published by Norman Baker. TNT stood for "The Naked Truth". Issues contain articles on the validity of Baker's cancer treatments, on the corrupt "medical trust," and other polemics.
- Baker Hospital/ Norman Baker, Eureka Springs, Arkansas, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Pamphlet on Baker Hospital titled Where Sick Folks Get Well: Without Operation, Radium, or X-ray, published by Norman Baker, Inc. The hospital was "owned and operated by Norman Baker." Baker did not have a medical degree.
- Cherokee Sanitarium/ Dr. R. C. Seaman, Cherokee, Iowa, ca. 1914 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Pamphlet by R. C. Seaman, Liquid Escharotic with Combinations for the Proper Treatment of Cancers, Tumors, Ulcers, Lupus and Abnormal Growths Without Chloroform or Ether. Cover title is Cancer Can Be Cured.
- Indianapolis Cancer Hospital/ Dr. Chas. C. Root and Dr. Chas. A. McNeill, ca. 1925 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Pamphlet about the hospital with cover title, Information and Evidence.
- The Industrial Clinic/ George Franklin Smith, Bicknell, Indiana, ca. 1934 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  A Successful Cure for Cancer by George Franklin Smith, Ph.D., M.D.
- Krebiozen Research Foundation, Chicago, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Report on Krebiozen, an Agent for the Treatment of Cancer. The pamphlet discusses research on Krebiozen from 1951 to 1954. The Medical Historical Library has a large Krebiozen collection.
- Dr. L. T. Leach/ Park View Sanatorium, Indianapolis, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  L. T. Leach, M.D., Facts About Cancer. Leon T. Leach had received a patent for Cancerol in 1905. Leach is criticized in the AMA pamphlet in Folder 1.
- The Mason Cancer Institute, New York, ca. 1900 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Abbot Myron Mason Chemical Co., Cancers, Tumors and the Malignant Blood Disorders and their Successful Cure by the Vitalia System of Treatment, 18th revised edition. Cover page title is "The Scientific Cure of...Cancer, Tumors, Scrofula and all Malignant Blood Disorders by the Mason Cancer Institute."
- The Dr. Nichols Sanatorium/ Perry Nichols, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  The Value of Escharotics, Medicines Which Will Destroy any Living or Fungus Tissue in the Treatment of Cancer, Lupus, Sarcoma, and Any Other Form of Malignancy. Perry Nichols, B.S., M.D., was formerly Professor of Malignant Diseases in the Lincoln Medical College, Lincoln, Nebraska. Later versions of this book can be found through the online catalog of Yale University.
  Soft leather-bound book with cover in relief illustrating the Sanatorium.
- H. C. Southworth, M.D., Binghamton, N.Y., ca. 1916 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  H. C. Southworth, What Others Say...A Permanent Cure.
- William Hoare Tomlinson, London, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  William Hoare Tomlinson, Cancer Profiteers: Suppression of Truth, London, ca. 1932. Leather covered book with bookplate of Frederick L. Hoffman, inscribed in ink to Dr. Percy Sargent, F.R.C.S., November 21, 1932. Tomlinson, described as a London medical practitioner, was promoting the Placentin Treatment.
- Williams Sanatorium/ Dr. Boyd T. Williams, Minneapolis, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Boyd T. Williams, The Williams Treatment for Cancer. A tipped-in page notes that the Sanatorium had moved to Hudson, Wisconsin.